[Applause]
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software this March 21st and 22nd
don't miss tech ignite in Burlingame
California just minutes from the San
Francisco Airport come to tech ignite to
get rock-solid info and forecasts on
adaptive cybersecurity emerging
technologies machine learning and deep
level operational intelligence and much
more join tech superstars Steve Wozniak
and Grady Booch plus sea level leaders
from Netflix Google IBM Salesforce GE
Digital in their town to gain valuable
insights and learn about real world
solutions you can start applying today
register now for the I Triple E computer
society's premier conference tech ignite
at tech ignite computer org and discover
the truth behind technology
for software engineering radio this is
Robert bloomin I have with me today
Donnie Nadal nee Donnie is a scale of
developer a pager duty working on
improving the reliability of their
back-end systems he spends a large
amount of time investigating problems
experienced with distributed systems
like Cassandra and zookeeper he runs the
failure Friday exercise a pager duty
Donnie is a graduate from Waterloo
University in economics Donnie
welcome to software engineering radio
thank you very much for having me we
will be talking today about debugging
distributed systems the idea for this
show came from a blog post called
zookeepers Poisson packet and a
conference talk on the same subject
which I saw Donnie give at the velocity
conference earlier in 2016 I wanted to
talk about the bug itself and some
lessons learned that can be applied to
distributed systems problems in general
first thing Donnie would you like to
tell the listeners anything else about
your background no I think you've pretty
much covered it okay
briefly tell us what is pager Duty's
application that you were working on
when this bug was discovered the core of
pager duties application is alerting
people when their software has problems
so you generally have a lot of different
monitoring systems they all hook up into
pager duty and then our software will
call or text or email your engineers to
let them know when you have a problem we
also have a lot of other things on top
of that to make it easier to coordinate
these responses and to fix things
quickly at the time I was working on a
few different back-end systems in what
we call the notification pipeline which
is the critical series of micro services
that we have which are necessary to take
an event coming in from our customers do
some processing on it and then actually
make the notification so call out to our
customers I'm going to guess that
people depend on this system when their
product is down that it would be very
important for your system not to have
any unplanned failures or downtime is
that correct absolutely we care a lot
about having highly available software
and our goal is to be able to what we
actually run our software across
multiple data centers and in fact across
multiple providers
so not just AWS also on an azure and the
goal is to be able to lose an entire
data center while still remaining
available right you talked about running
on AWS I'd like to introduce the concept
of a region what is a region in AWS a
region is one of the units of fault
tolerance that AWS gives you so a region
is made up of multiple availability
zones and an availability zone you can
think of it as a data center although
really an availability zone can be made
up of multiple data centers multiple
buildings but they're very very close
together and within a region different
availability zones are also very close
together AWS has the the goal of having
each availability zone which is within a
region each availability zone should be
a unit of fault tolerance so it should
be nearly impossible for all of the
availability zones in a region to go
down although it has happened before so
internally in pager duty we tend to
think of a single region as a single
data center and so we spread out across
multiple regions the point being then
these units of fault tolerance are
things which can fail independently of
each other
and you give yourself some redundancy by
using more than one yeah that's right
okay so in AWS their regions are called
things like US West one US East one why
would system span multiple regions well
the idea is that because a region can go
down even though it it shouldn't go down
it should really only be an availability
that that availability zone that
a region can go down and so by spreading
across multiple regions it means that if
you have proper replication and things
like that you ought to be able to lose a
region and a region when when you're
talking about us East one us West one
that is a very tight geographic that's a
really tight grouping of buildings
together so if there were for an example
an earthquake around there even though
you're in multiple availability zones
it's possible that it could damage all
of those availability zones sure it
could be something even though AWS did a
great job building their data centers
out and the electricity and heating and
cooling it could be something totally
out of their control like a natural
disaster yep and a good example of where
even if you have lots of redundancy in
your power or things like that you have
backup generators you still have to have
those machines be connected to other
ones through your network and you can
have redundant paths for your network
but a natural disaster is the kind of
thing that could take out all of your
network connections to the rest of the
internet or to other regions
sure are you aware whether Amazon routes
across the public internet between
regions or if they have their own
dedicated bandwidth that they lease I
believe they have both so they I believe
they do have peering agreements that can
go across the public internet but they
do have their own fiber at least for
most regions and I think for all and
that's what they use primarily there's
actually a case I think about a year ago
or so that we experienced where there
was a fiber cut and the latency in one
of the regions that we were in to some
of the other ones it went from being you
know 20 milliseconds or so all the way
up to being I think around 100
milliseconds because I think the theory
was that AWS was actually routing
through their own fiber as much as they
could but it meant they were routing
packets kind of partway around the world
even though the the two places were
really close and if you went over the
public Internet then the network
connection would be fast but because
they were routing over their own
internal network maybe for cost reasons
the the latency was quite high for
several hours the problem we're gonna be
discussing it originated in a component
called zookeeper we did an entire show
number 229 on zookeeper I'd like you to
briefly tell us what is zookeeper and
what is a zookeeper cluster sure so
zookeeper is a distributed system which
is useful for building other distributed
systems what it gives you is it exposes
kind of a file system like interface to
you except you don't store regular files
in it you store little bits of
configuration information or
coordination information so you can do
things like create a directory create a
file atomically update a file you can
create a file where the name is
guaranteed to be sequential if you have
multiple concurrent clients that are
trying to create the same file you can
also have a file that will go away when
the client disconnects now the idea with
the zookeeper is that you then build on
top of these this small set of
primitives to build other primitives of
you know varying degrees of how
high-level they are so you can use this
to build distributed locking where you
want to make sure that only one node in
the distributed system that you're
building is a leader for example or it
can take a lock on some entity or some
set of entities you can also use it
while you probably not recommended but
you could use it for service discovery
where you would create a file with
information like your IP and your port
that's how to contact you and all of
your different clients would create that
and to do service discovery to pick
which node you want to contact you just
look in that directory and you pick one
at random and it will most likely be
live because when it disconnects
shortly after that the file would go
away at pager duty we use it mostly for
distributive locking where we use it to
protects different entities from
concurrent and modification
one of the reasons we do that is because
we use Cassandra and it doesn't really
give real acid transactions they do have
what they call lightweight transactions
but they're not quite as useful as you
might think so we use zookeeper as a way
to prevent as a way to kind of gain some
of the benefits of a transaction that we
some level of isolation from that a
zookeeper cluster is how zookeeper is
highly available when you run zookeeper
you typically run it as in a cluster of
three or five nodes at page.you duty we
typically use five and what zookeeper
does is it will first elect a leader and
then all operations all right operations
flow through the leader that's how I can
do things like give you sequentially
named files when you try to create them
concurrently and the idea is that if the
zookeeper leader fails one of the
replicas can take over because before it
will have told the client that a write
was performed it will have replicated
that to at least a majority of the
zookeeper nodes so in that way you can
have the kind of the extra abstraction a
zookeeper be highly available where any
node can fail and you haven't lost any
data okay I can see how that would be
very useful in your business because in
order to ensure that your system is
always delivering messages you need to
have a lot of redundancy because pieces
of the system might fail but then when
you have a lot of nodes that might not
be trying to do the same thing or to
cooperate in doing something you don't
want you want to ensure that everything
that needs to be done gets done exactly
once and not zero times or three times
you know that's right okay why does the
zookeeper cluster need to elect a leader
in order to give some of the consistency
guarantees that a zookeeper offers you
it's very very helpful to have all of
these operations go through a single
node that way it can do whatever
coordination it needs on its own
so in zookeeper any right
to go through the leader so in order to
have your cluster be available it has to
elect a leader first I'd like to discuss
a bug that you presented at velocity
let's start with what was the first
indication that something was not right
the first indication that we had that
there was a problem was actually with
our regular application level monitoring
that we had what it had told us was that
basically just things were becoming
stale work wasn't being done and we
ended up tracing that during the during
the outage we ended up tracing that to
zookeeper not being able to do any work
see your your monitoring was telling you
that the system was was stuck how did
you narrow down the problem to zookeeper
I believe what we had done in at least
the the first instance that we had of
this happening in product in production
was just through the logs we were able
to see that we were timing out when
trying to talk to zookeeper so you have
a client and it was trying to connect to
zookeeper and it was timing out either
getting a connection or requested
zookeeper to do some work and that
request timed out yep that's right it
was requesting a zookeeper to do some
work either reads or writes both of them
were failing I'm sorry the error
manifested in production were you able
to reproduce that in a isolated
environment until we were actually able
to figure out what was going on
we couldn't reproduce it so we we did
try quite a bit to reproduce it in our
low testing environment but we we were
never successful until the very end when
we actually knew what was going on okay
so what was the next step
one one quick thing I should probably
mention is that one of one of the
symptoms that we had seen was that even
though zookeeper wasn't able to do any
work the all of the processes were of
all the processes were up so it it
seemed like it should be a
- but it wasn't actually able to do the
client was timing out probably the next
thing you would want to look at is
zookeeper and see if there are any clues
there am I right about that yeah that's
right
so we we do have some good dashboards
for zookeeper what they had showed us
was that all of the zookeeper processes
were up there was a leader for the
cluster but the cluster was completely
hung when we checked the the networking
between them that was also fine at least
at the time that we checked there there
was a network blip that had happened a
little bit before but when we checked
the network was completely healthy the
cluster was up but for some reason it
wasn't actually able to do any work when
you say the cluster was hung what what
exactly do you mean the the processes
were running but if you try to do a read
or write then it would just timeout were
there any error messages log messages
health checks anything that gave you
more insight into why it got into that
state so one of the annoying things
about this was that the health checks
that we were using at least for
zookeeper were all fine
so there is a very popular health check
that a lot of people use for zookeeper
which is you can connect on a certain
port you can issue it the the
four-letter command are you okay and it
will reply back saying I'm okay if if
it's up and if it thinks everything is
good now we did have monitoring or not
we had that command running regularly
but it actually showed that the
zookeeper was reporting everything was
okay now we we looked in the zookeeper
logs and they're worth some kind of
weird looking things in the zookeeper
logs that we that we did try to
investigate what what's one of those for
example
so one of them was this concept of
zookeeper trying to take a snapshot
zookeeper as I mentioned earlier it's a
gives you this abstraction of a file
system one thing I didn't mention was
that you're you're meant to put in only
really small configuration information
or coordination information and this is
meant to fit in memory so the the entire
debate database for zookeeper is usually
pretty small just a few Meg's or maybe
tens of Meg's and it keeps a log of
operations that you've done to it now
what it does is every once in a while it
will write out a complete snapshot of
this in memory database so that when you
crash and recover it can just read in
the snapshot instead of having to replay
a gigantic log of everything you've done
since the beginning of time now one of
the early suspicious log entries that we
had seen was this log entry saying that
it was too busy to take a snapshot and
that it was going to skip that snapshot
now when we looked into the code to see
what that meant it meant that it was
actually in the process of writing out a
snapshot when it tried to take a second
one now looking at a timeout of one it
we had taken the the previous snapshot
it several minutes had gone by before it
was taking or before it attempted to
take the second one that had been
skipped so initially we thought that
maybe there was some problem where that
first snapshot was taking a really long
time to write out and was then blocking
this other one from happening maybe
because of I know some some disk
problems or things like that okay
do you take it as far as you could with
information that zookeeper was already
giving you you didn't have a solution
what was the next step in your
investigation well one of the things
that we had tried was so what one of the
key things that you want is obviously to
be able to reproduce a bug it makes it
much much easier to figure out what's
going on if you can reproduce that at
will because then you can do this in
your own kind of staging environment or
row test environment and then you can be
a lot more
aggressive at poking at zookeeper or
about enabling reliever both logging to
let you know what's going on so we we
struggled for quite a long time trying
to be able to reproduce this the closest
that we had got was actually raid elated
to that that log line of trying to take
a snapshot we ended up reproducing what
would happen if there was a really slow
disk so a nice tool that we used for
this was a tool called sshfs which lets
you mount a remote directory of any
machine that you have SSH access to so
we did that we configured zookeeper to
put its files on that remotely mounted
filesystem and then you can use your
normal network tools like IP tables or
TC to mess with the network to make it
be slow or to hang and those things will
manifest as disk problems by either the
disk being slow or the disk hanging now
we had actually managed to get zookeeper
to hang in a similar fashion by slowing
down the disk like that now that seemed
quite promising at first but after we
had investigated a bit more we have
other other monitoring and other
dashboards showing us disk metrics and
things like that and even though it
seemed quite promising at first we ended
up concluding that that wasn't what was
happening because our other monitoring
showed us that really there there wasn't
any disk problems at the time there were
other log files that were being written
out fine and as I said earlier the this
in-memory database but this snapshot
that it was writing out was really small
so it would have to be really severe io
problems for it to actually hang for as
long as it seemed like it was hanging
with this this log line of it saying
that it was skipping this snapshot many
minutes after it had started the
previous one you went down this path
that turned out to be a dead end
then you did have a breakthrough that
enabled you to make significant progress
what was the big step forward that got
you closer to what was going on
so the way that we got that next step
was by adding some extra monitoring to
zookeeper so I'd mentioned earlier that
this are you ok health check showed that
zookeeper itself thought that it was
healthy what we had added was an
external health check that was just
simple it would just do a right to a key
in zookeeper and then it would try to
read that one now we added that health
check and the next time that this is
this had happened in production we
managed to grab a stack trace from the
leader at the time and it was this stack
trace while the cluster was in this kind
of up but stuck state that let us figure
out what was going on she added this
more intrusive health check what was the
thinking there of why that would be
useful check well what we had seen was
that zookeeper itself thought it was
healthy but the application wasn't
actually able to make any progress by
reading or writing to zookeeper
now having a really general health check
on the application as close as you can
to what the user would see is very
useful because it means that you can
catch any problem or pretty much any
problem even ones that you haven't even
thought of dependencies that you
recently added or anything like that
because you have a this health check of
pretty much the the customer or your
user actually being able to do things
now the problem is that that doesn't
give you any information about which of
your dependencies have problems or
what's really going on so that that was
part of the reasoning of wanting to add
the second one and as though it was also
just the observation that our
application wasn't able to read and
write so we wanted to have this extra
independent check of whether or not
something could read or write to
zookeeper because it seemed pretty
likely that zookeeper did have a problem
but it could have been that our
application itself was the one that had
a bug that caused it to not be able to
read or write to zookeeper and that
zookeeper itself was healthy the whole
time I see the built in health check you
ask
zookeeper are you okay it says yeah sure
I'm okay but it might be lying too and
maybe the only thing that its able to do
is say yes I'm okay not able to perform
its other functions that you have that
you really need it to do yep that's
right when you look into the code that
are you okay check is really just a very
tight mapping of it will take the
command as long as it can receive that
command it will reply with I'm okay it
doesn't do any extra check itself to
make sure that it's actually healthy
it's really not much more than just
checking that the port is open and that
zookeeper has somewhat started up okay
let's talk about this stack trace what
did you see what we'd seen was one of
the threads on the leader stuck trying
to serialize a snapshot of the database
to the follower so the zookeeper runs as
a cluster you have the leader you have
all the followers and it if you remember
it keeps this log of what operations
you've performed but when a follower
disconnects from the leader and then
starts back up again it has to catch up
to where the leader is right now so
often it will just be able to grab the
operations that happened recently the
zookeeper leader stores them in memory
so it will just replay those operations
to the follower but if the follower is
too far behind then it has to send a
full snapshot of the database to the
follower now this was where it seemed to
get stuck so it was a follower had
disconnected it had reconnected it had
requested a snapshot the leader was
sending a snapshot to the follower but
it was blocking when it was trying to
write to that socket to the follower
when you looked at the code that was
indicated in the stack trace did you get
more insight into what was going wrong
yeah well the the key problem here was
that when it writes out that snapshot to
a follower it has to iterate all over
all of the items in this in memory
database now when it does that it enters
a Java synchronized block for each item
now because it did that
and because it got stuck that meant that
this thread that was trying to write at
the snapshot to the follower was holding
on to a Java synchronized or holding on
to a Java lock for one of those items if
you were to try to perform an operation
on this item that the the that had the
lock taken on it then of course you
would block now the zookeeper works by
having a series of threads that process
the requests that come in they each do
different things so there's a thread
that's responsible for writing it to the
filesystem to replicating it to
followers to actually performing the
operation on the in-memory database and
these threads or what one of these
threads would then become stuck because
it tried to take that lock that was
being held by one of the by the thread
that was writing at the snapshot and
this actually explained kind of one of
the mysteries that we had seen before
that I hadn't mentioned earlier which is
that sometimes the cluster would hang by
having the leader just come to a dead
stop it would it would stop performing
new operations but sometimes the leader
would actually fall behind the rest of
the cluster and operations would still
happen for a little while and then they
would hang and we ended up realizing
that the reason this was happening was
because depending on what kind of
operation you tried to perform on this
item that was that was blocked by this
other thread you could hang near the end
of this chain that does things after it
was able to replicate that request to a
follower or you might hang right at the
beginning of that chain before it was
able to replicate a request to a
follower yeah
I'm looking at this code right now if a
synchronized block then right to a
network that sounds like a dangerous
coding practice something that could
definitely go wrong when you're holding
locks on things and doing operations
that have potential of lasting a long
time yeah absolutely
so one
one problem here is that you're taking a
lock on an item and then doing this
operation that could in this case a
network right which could block for a
long time now one of the surprising
things to me is how long this operation
could block so normally you think of a
network right sure it could block for a
little bit but even if there was some it
it would only kind of block and kill
there was a connection problem and then
the socket would disconnect but what we
had seen was actually this problem
lasting for well over ten minutes I
think nearly fifteen minutes in one case
that we saw of having the cluster in
this state where it's blocked trying to
do the right and this the TCP socket
that you're trying to write to is just
hung for that entire period of time when
you found this problem in the code the
cause of the stack trace and that was
not the final step in debugging the
problem no it it really just pointed us
to more things that we needed to figure
out to really understand what was going
on here so after you found this stack
trace you identified where it was
failing what was the next problem that
led you to well the the next thing that
we realized once we knew that the code
was blocking in this way we could figure
out why one of the followers wasn't
taking over from the leader because the
way that we resolved this when it
happened was just by killing the leader
so restart the leader process and then
immediately one of the followers would
take over and operations would continue
as normal but the thing is that you're
not supposed to need to do that manually
part of the benefit of zookeeper being
in a cluster and using a consensus
algorithm it can figure out or it should
be able to figure out automatically that
something is wrong and one of the other
followers should be able to take over
now the way that it did this is by
having the leader send a heartbeat to
the followers so every few seconds I
think it is the leader will send a
heartbeat to the followers and the
followers will keep track of how
recently they've heard this
heartbeat from the leader and if it's
been too long then they kick off an
election now when we dug into the code a
bit more we realized why this wasn't
happening which was that this thread
that sends out heartbeats to the leader
or the this process of the leader
sending out hurt beats to the followers
is actually done by a completely
separate thread so even though most of
the important threads on zookeeper are
blocked or are unable to do any kind of
work you still have this one thread off
on the side
sending heartbeats to the followers
saying don't take over essentially this
sounds a little bit like the problem
with the health check where the system
was doing just enough to pass certain
checks but not doing the things you
needed it to do yep I think this is
actually a pretty big problem in a lot
of distributed systems in any kind of
leader based system like this you
usually have some kind of timeout or
heartbeat or things like that that are
being sent now the problem is that if
this heart beat or whatever it is you're
sending if you don't first check to make
sure that you're actually able to make
progress then you can end up in this
situation where the only thing that the
leader is able to do is send out thing
send up this message saying I'm healthy
don't take over even though all of the
important things aren't able to happen
from that point what was the next stage
in your investigation
so the the next step was digging into
this TCB behavior to figure out why this
why this TCP connection was stuck for so
long now we did have a little bit of
network trouble before these outages
happened but when we at the time that we
would investigate the network was
actually healthy but for some reason it
was still blocked the TCP connection was
still stuck ok
in my experience debugging these type of
transitions are very important where
you've decided we've extracted
everything we can from this layer the
Java layer the problem isn't there we
need to change where we're looking to
another layer how did you determine that
the problem wasn't or you weren't going
to get any more progress out of looking
at the Java and zookeeper and you had to
go down to the network layer well it was
really about trying to find a full
explanation for what had happened so
even though we had gone through the code
we had figured out what was happening in
zookeeper and in fact by this point we
knew enough that we could fix it and the
the fix is at least that we implemented
was just not doing a this network
blocking right not doing that within the
synchronized block instead in the
synchronized block you just take an
in-memory copy of the thing that you
want to write and then outside of that
block perform the write that way even if
it does get stuck all the important
threads are still able to do what they
need because you haven't blocked one of
the objects that they're trying to take
a lock on so even though we had somewhat
figured out what was going on there we
wanted to dig deeper to figure out why
this TCP connection could be stuck for
so long yeah and this illustrates
another important lesson about this
story with an open source project you
can modify the code and deploy your own
hatched version of the project to test
out bug fixes yep and in fact we did run
our own patched version for quite a
while while we were waiting for a new
release of zookeeper to be put out which
had incorporated our patch yeah I'm
going on a bit of a tangent away from
the investigation how did the zookeeper
community respond were they were they
did you get any inspiration from the
community in and were you in
communication with them around this
issue we had opened up a ticket on their
ticket tracker describing what this
problem was that we had seen and
actually we didn't even open that up
until we had a fix for it that we had
tried out and once we had that they were
they were very receptive and quite happy
to incorporate it into the project going
back to the investigation then you'd
determined that the TCP behavior was not
well understood how did you proceed with
your investigation from that point
well the big thing that didn't make
sense was a connection on the leader
being in the established state and
blocking this that this blocking right
coming from Java staying there and and
being blocked while this connection was
established and yet on the follower side
it didn't know about this connection at
all it had already forgotten about it or
or something like that and yet it was
still established and we had seen this
staying staying in this state for many
minutes
yes TCP it's a state machine and the two
ends should ideally agree on what the
state of the connection is or they
should reach an agreement fairly quickly
is that correct yep under normal
circumstances they should what was going
on then we decided to look into what
happened to what happens to TCP
connections under packet loss or under
network isolation so one of the things
that we started experimenting with was
establishing it a connection and then
introducing a network partition so that
these two sides of the TCP connection
can't talk to each other and then having
one of the sides kind of playing the
role of the leader do a write and watch
what happens with retries watch what
happens to the connection state when
does it get terminated how long does it
take those kinds of things so what kind
of a tools did you use to examine this
what's very helpful for this is using
TCP dump which will capture all the
packets that are being sent and then
copying that over to your machine and
opening it up in Wireshark to take a
look as well as using netstat regularly
to look at the state of the connection
and of course IP tables to block packets
did this issue have something to do with
the cluster having members in different
data centers having to go across much
longer network paths then within a
single LAN to an extent yes these kinds
of problems can happen when you're
running just within one data center but
they're much more likely to happen when
you're running across multiple data
centers and in this case it was going
over the public Internet because these
were two data centers that were being
run by different hosting providers so
even though these things can happen in
kind of a local network or in one data
center a lot of these problems are much
more likely or they can persist for a
lot longer you can have much
hi packet loss lasting for a lot longer
when you're running over a wide area
network
are you aware within the distributed
systems feel generally are do a lot of
bugs tend to surface when people build
these bigger clusters that span across
the public Internet well I think even
now it's still fairly rare to run these
systems across multiple data centers
across the public internet separated by
real wide area network latency rather
than just really small amounts so with
with Cassandra in particular there are
some people who are doing that although
their setup is usually a little bit
different from ours they're doing more
of an asynchronous replication between
their data centers doing writes with a
consistency level of what they call
local quorum meaning you only care about
the consistency within one data center
and then that will be asynchronously
replicated across to another one in our
Cassandra clusters we use the regular
quorum consistency which will
synchronously replicate across a
different data center and in zookeeper
it's basically always like that and will
always be running at kind of the
equivalent of what Cassandra would call
quorum consistency where you always
write to the majority so if your nodes
are across a wide area network then you
will always be writing across the
network
hmm so the in your presentation there's
about 15 slides dealing with the TCP
protocol could you condense down what
you eventually found to be the cause of
these long long time outs sure the the
kind of root problem with with what we
were seeing was you can have a follower
and a leader they establish a TCP
connection if you introduce a network
partition between them so they aren't
allowed to communicate and you try to
write on the leader it will try to send
this packet the follower and it will
wait to hear an acknowledgment back if
it doesn't hear that acknowledgement
back it will keep on retrying increasing
the delay between subsequent attempts of
re trying to send this packet and
actually gets up to be quite a high
delay in these retries so the the
maximum which is hard-coded in the
kernel is it will wait 120 seconds
between retrying and it's doing a
doubling behavior of each retry that
does and it will wait for many many
retries 15 retries and so when you put
all that together when you try to do a
write and there's a network partition
that right could block for at least 15
minutes and it could be higher depending
on some other parameters and kind of the
the initial network latency that was
going on this what then you say
hard-coded was this something you could
fix by tuning some of the kernel
parameters about TCP behavior you could
kind of work around this indirectly but
the only tunable parameter that would
affect this is the number of retries
that you allow TCP to do when it doesn't
hear back this acknowledgment so if you
lowered that then you would indirectly
get kind of a lower you could think of
it as a time-out on when you were doing
or right but it's an indirect way and
it's kind of not really ideal because
then if you do have packet loss you
would get fewer retries before it would
just give
I have been intending to make some of
these parameters a bit more configurable
because what I would like to have is
keep the number of retries the same or
even increase the number of retries but
cap that maximum retry time out at some
configurable parameters so that you
could set it to be quite a bit less than
120 seconds
yeah that's pretty long there's one
other slide I found quite interesting it
talks about IP tables and netstat now
those are two tools in the Linux world
that there's a lot of Linux tools and
they're not all distinct there's a lot
of overlap between what they do
the interesting point on this slide it
says IP tables connections not equal to
netstat connections explain what that
means I'd mentioned earlier how when you
try to do this right if you have a full
network partition between these two
sides then you could have that right be
blocked for 15 minutes or more but that
wasn't quite what we were seeing because
when we went to investigate the network
health we saw that the network was
actually healthy but the connection was
still stuck so we to figure out why that
was happening what we ended up seeing
was that the follower side or one of the
sides of the connection that wasn't
trying to do this right would disconnect
it would try to close this TCP
connection but there was still a network
partition so it wouldn't be able to send
this fin packet the it trying to tell
the other side that it wants to close
connection right it wouldn't be able oh
sorry yeah so the fin packet that's part
of the TCP state machine where it's
trying to the two sides are trying to
agree to close a connection yep that's
right yes okay it's trying to close the
connection but if you have a network
partition obviously that's not going to
get to the other side but you don't want
to have this this state kind of that
you're the this connection that you're
trying to close remain there
indefinitely so after a certain amount
of time you just consider the connection
closed even though you haven't been able
to talk to the other side
now we were running iptables as a
firewall to only allow certain
connections through only connections in
certain ports or establish connections
that you knew about
now this follower side what would happen
is it would close the connection or it
would make the attempt to close the
connection it wouldn't be able to tell
the other side but it would eventually
mark it as closed but now the network
can heal and one of those retries from
the other side that's waiting this
15-minute time one of those could come
through but iptables would then block
this packet because it didn't know about
that connection and so in this way you
can have these two sides where one of
them considers the connection
established one of them considers it
closed and even though the retries are
coming in that one side is blocking
those packets and so you never get this
other TCP packet that would come through
a reset packet which is normally what
would happen when you try to talk to a
machine that didn't know about the
connection but because iptables was
blocking it it would never get through
and so the network can heal but you
still have this connection stuck now to
get to the point about these iptables
connections are not equal to netstat
connections what I hadn't realized was
that iptables has its own state machine
that it uses completely separate from
the regular kernel state machine so you
can and in fact the IP table side just
uses simple timers that are different
than the knowledge of the kernel of
whatever retries it has an exponential
back-off and things like that
IP tables just has simple timers that it
uses based on watching packets come in
and out and it turns out that that time
or at least with the default behavior it
can actually consider a connection be
closed after one side attempts to close
it earlier than the regular TCP kernel
view of that connection so you can in
fact have if you do this setup of having
a network partition have once I tried it
right now the other side try to close it
wait for a little while you can be
watching netstat
and see the connection still be there in
the I think it would be the Finn wait
connection or I forgot which TCP state
it would be in while you're waiting for
it to be closed you could see that in
netstat but iptables might have already
forgotten about the connection and so if
the network had healed right then you
could have packets come in you could see
on that other side it still knows about
the connection but iptables would drop
it and so you would still not get that
reset packet going back so the reason I
I found that interesting when I was
thinking about the outline for the show
one of the points I'd written down on
lessons learned was that these tools we
rely on why or maybe that's overstated
but it's definitely a theme in your
discussion that you have these health
checks and heartbeats and tools and they
tell you one thing but you can't always
take it at face value it doesn't
necessarily mean exactly what you might
think it means I think one of the things
that made this problem difficult to
investigate but also really interesting
to investigate is when you have to go a
kind of go really deep go beyond the
regular layers that you're looking at in
this case digging really deep into what
happens with TCP behavior under network
isolation and yeah really kind of
understanding or in my case learning a
lot of these different tools to figure
out what the real state is I spent quite
a lot of time playing around with a few
machines introducing network isolation
and then watching what actually happened
with what watching what actually
happened to the TCP state and to the
retries that were going on and actually
ended up seeing kind of some maybe
undocumented behavior or maybe a bug in
the the TCP kernel stack where you end
up getting one extra retry than you
would think
are we still learning more about TCP and
how it behaves in edge
cases well I think a lot of people if
you're never forced to go digging into
it you kind of take it for granted
that you establish a TCP connection you
write stuff over it and everything is
fine if things go wrong then it gets
disconnected it's kind of these weird
edge cases that come up that can really
throw off your understanding or force
you to dig into what's going on there so
there's one more layer in debugging
about IPSec and I'm gonna skip that but
people who are interested should look at
your slide share and willing to that in
the slip in the show notes I want to get
more into lessons learned that the rest
of us can apply in debugging problems
that we have what is a key lesson that
you you learned as a an engineer from
investigating this problem I think the
biggest one that I learned is not really
a technical thing but it's more that you
need to be really persistent so when we
were debugging this problem
there were several days in a row where I
came into work and the entire day I
spent looking at logs going through
zookeeper code and basically not making
any progress I was making some progress
in terms of gaining an understanding of
zookeeper and of TCP behavior and other
things like that but in terms of making
real tangible progress to figure out
what was going on it was just no
progress at all so I am very glad that
we were persistent in in this
investigation to figure out what was
really going on
I've had the experience debugging and
and I don't have this experience writing
code but I've had some debug with bug
chasing where I start to despair and I
think I am never going to find this it's
just too hard did you ever experience
despair or the feeling the thinking I'm
just gonna give up or did you always
have optimism that you would find the
root cause well I wouldn't say that I
had optimism the whole time but I never
really had that kind of despair it was a
little discouraging to to go for so long
and to not make any progress in terms of
kind of the boolean measure of have I
figured it out or not but luckily I
never really ran out I ran out of ideas
of what to try next I had lots of ideas
of things that it could be or or kind of
the next step of something new that I
should investigate or some new bit of
the code that I should look at or things
like that you gave this presentation
about the problem the full investigation
were you the sole person working on it
or were there multiple people nope there
were multiple people so I think I was
the one who investigated for the longest
but I had a couple of my co-workers who
had were kind of on and off this
investigation and also some others who I
asked about networking behavior who kind
of gave me some pointers of where to
investigate next the problem as he
chased it around it was from Java to the
Linux kernel to the TCP protocol often
people will not have a really deep
knowledge of all those layers did you
collaborate with people who were expert
each at a different layer or how did
that work well I'm fairly experienced in
Java so I didn't have too much trouble
going through the codebase for the for
the zookeeper code which is written in
Java it was really the networking
behavior that I needed a tip from what
my colleagues Evan who was kind of gave
me that tip about TCP being able to or
really paying attention to the state
that the connection is in particularly
under network isolation you have a
number of lessons learned what is
another key lesson you learned from this
process one of the interesting things
that I thought about during this was how
interfaces or abstract methods can make
it a bit harder to be confident that
your code is correct
so with this call in zookeeper that was
taking a lock and then performing this
potentially blocking operation this TCP
call which as we learned can block for
quite a bit longer than you might expect
I had thought about how the the call
that it was performing that ended up
writing over at the socket was actually
an interface method so with that even
though I don't think it was a factor in
this specific one it's easy to imagine a
situation where you're writing code
where you take a lock and then you call
out to an interface or some Hofstra
abstract method and at the time you
write that code all of the
implementations of that are non-blocking
they all operate just in memory they're
guaranteed to finish in a certain amount
of time but it's possible for somebody
later on to add a new implementation of
that which would all of a sudden make
your existing code incorrect and again
as I said I don't think that came into
play here but it was just a kind of an
interesting thing that I noticed that it
can make this kind of analysis or this
kind of problem a bit easier to occur
than you might think yeah I have seen
some critiques of object-oriented
programming that raised this point that
by creating abstract methods and
interfaces you can't guarantee that all
the implementations that people will
plug in will honor all of the contracts
that are assumed by the frameworks or
higher-level
so of the stack that call them
and I think this illustrates that point
I want to summarize in some of the
lessons we talked about earlier were
about monitoring and health checks what
did you learn about that so I feel I
think even strong more strongly now than
I did before that it's really good to
have high high level health checks of
your application to make sure that you
can catch all these different things but
also that it's very useful to have kind
of these narrow but still intend tests
of dependencies that you have it then
makes it very easy when you get paged
and you see instead of just getting a
message saying that you know there's
some problem in the application it's
good to get that rather than nothing but
it's also nice to have either another
alert or a dashboard that shows you and
here's the the one dependency that is
messing up right so you want computers
to do as much work as they can in
collecting useful information about the
problem before you start working on it
yep okay yeah and what about health
checks
health checks are another thing that I
think could be improved in a lot of
systems so it it's very easy to make
kind of a naive health check that just
replies and says that you're healthy as
long as the process is up but you can
have this problem where that's then the
only thing that is healthy so I think
it's also important to tie in more of a
deep health check whenever you're doing
that kind of thing
don't just reply right away saying that
it's good either perform an actual
operation as your health check or
something along those lines and I think
that this is important for for one part
for monitoring the dependencies of this
is a great way of checking your
dependency perform a simple operation
and that's their measurement of whether
your dependency is healthy but it's also
useful in any kind of leader follower
based system where the leader is
preventing followers from taking over to
do some kind of deeper health check
locally to make sure that when you're
getting requests you are actually able
to process them and it's only then if
you know that to be true that you would
then send out this message to your
followers saying you know don't take
over everything is good sure this this
reminds me of a retail system I worked
on we use external monitoring service
called Pingdom that checks that your
servers respond to http we also
implemented check that would log into
the site create a customer buy a product
put it in the cart and check-out or
cancel the charge at the last second
because if you can respond to HTTP but
you can't allow people to buy products
then something's not right yep
absolutely that's a great thing to do
you can pick kind of whatever your most
important feature is in the case of a
shopping site can you go and actually
add and buy a product and that's a great
health check to use so Pedro duty also
has a similar system we call a watchdog
that performs end-to-end testing against
our system where it acts
as a customer would by sending events to
a regular public endpoint using our
public API to perform various operations
that we think are important and then
making sure that it actually gets
delivered in the end and that's a system
that we run against production but
because it's kind of a outside of our
regular system and only uses our public
endpoints you can even point that at any
of our different environments and use
that to check that for example the the
load test or different staging
environments are healthy as well yeah
and now there's one more lesson which I
learned from your experience and also
from reading the blog post about the
zookeepers poison packet which describes
a different but similar bug and and I'm
not sure if you learn this lesson
because I think maybe you already knew
it and so you didn't need to learn it
but I come from a software development
background and the mindset is there's a
bug there's a bug in my code so I'm
gonna look in my code and find where the
problem is and I'm just gonna keep
looking in my code until I find it or
maybe the libraries if they're open
source and they're in the same language
or same stack I made a transition in my
current job to DevOps where one of the
big shift is we're looking at a lot more
layers of the stack a lot of the issues
I deal with is any possible layer could
fail sometimes multiple at once and just
opened up my mind a lot more to all the
different places that things could fail
and that I can't come into issue with
too much of a preconceived idea about
where the failure is so that isn't
really a question but you can comment on
that if you like or we can go to the
next next question it certainly makes it
harder to figure out what's going on
when you can't just assume that it's
your code that's wrong when you have to
go into these other layers or other
systems
that maybe had guarantees or met maybe
you thought they had certain guarantees
but it turns out that they don't it
makes it quite a bit harder to debug for
sure so this will be my final question
Donnie in reading the blog post about
zookeepers poison packet which has a lot
in common with the issue we've been
discussing today the problems were not
the result of one single bug in one
behavior whose interaction of multiple
bugs or not even bugs but behaviors that
were not well understood that interacted
with each other to produce the final
problem do you have any thoughts why is
it that we get these type of multiple
failures why isn't it just one thing
well in insecurity they have the concept
of defense-in-depth where you want to
have multiple layers of protection and
in a way you in a lot of distributed
systems you often get that when you have
this replication usually you can just
suffer the failure of a node and you're
fine these problems come up my question
is this because at the level you're
building a system like this you have a
wealth of best practices in knowledge
you know how to plan for ok a node fails
ok the cluster loses a member the easy
cases you've thought of them and that
leaves the hard cases yeah I think in a
lot of ways it's when your assumptions
are violated that then you start to have
problems like these so in the in this a
zookeeper problem that we've talked
about today they the assumption that was
probably made that TCP won't block for
that long so even though I might take a
variety of failures or some weird
Network conditions to expose this most
of the time it wouldn't happen but there
is this case when it can happen and that
assumption being violated that means
that you can have this bug in the
Poisson packet example it was not just
assumption but supposed to be a
guarantee that TCP won't corrupt your
data it has checksums that are supposed
to prevent that but in the kind of
multiple cascading problems or multiple
combined problems we did end up having
TCP data be corrupted and then the bad
part there was that the failure mode of
zookeeper when that happened end up
being in this stuck state rather than
being able to clean the crash and let
another node take over I think this is
another tough problem to deal with it's
when you have a node in this sort of
degraded state where it's not completely
healthy but it's healthy enough to say
to kind of occasionally send out
heartbeats or healthy enough to start
taking requests but not healthy enough
to finish them in in a reasonable amount
of time that makes me think about how as
programmers were trained to think in
layers if I'm implementing zookeeper
zookeeper deals with a network that's
another layer so I'm going to make some
assumptions about that layer as a
programmer and if I don't have in-depth
knowledge of TCP I'm gonna probably make
maybe a little more optimistic or
best-case assumptions about the network
which are ok as long as they're true but
then sometimes they're not yep having
these different layers having it be well
encapsulated like that it means that you
can be a lot more productive because you
now don't have to worry about kind of
data being ordered within TCP or about
corruption or anything like that you
just use this nice abstraction which
makes it a lot easier for you to build a
system but then when your assumptions
are violated you can have problems one
interesting one that I thought of a
while ago is that you have this
guarantee in TCP that data is ordered so
when you write it even if the individual
packets are delivered out of order TCP
will reconstruct them and give them to
you in the right order now the kind of
really edge case that I thought of is
that what happens when you then
disconnect or if you have some of they
have two packet loss usually what your
client or what your system will do is it
will establish a new TCP connection now
the ordering bit of data between those
two connections isn't guaranteed at all
because they're different connections
and you can think of maybe a
pathological case where one side will
have written some data that will have
been you know it will be it will suffer
packet loss and it will be retried and
in that time you go and you establish a
new connection and you write some new
data but now this thing that you sent
second will actually come first and the
other side might even get that data that
you sent initially later on and that
could cause problems so even though you
have this abstraction of TCP s or
you potentially could have this weird
edge case of well maybe it's not yeah it
does exactly illustrate that now a
minute ago I said it was gonna be my
last question but I thought of one more
in the programming job market the
emphasis it's very focused on what
skills people have people will list
their Java program or Python Linux on
their resume do you think of that
debugging is a distinct skill set that
can differentiate you and make you more
valuable to a company well it's an
interesting question so I I certainly
think that debugging skills make you
more valuable and that they're extremely
useful I don't know whether I can say
for sure that it's a distinct skill I
think maybe it is but I'm not quite sure
okay
wrapping up we have talked about the
zookeeper blog SlideShare are there any
other resources or anything you
personally post that you would like to
people to have a look at well I keep a
pretty low profile online so I don't
have too much to share from that one
thing I would like to to pitch though is
this the concept of doing fault
injection or we call it failure Friday
Netflix is going to term chaos
engineering I think that's a very useful
thing to to do to distributed systems
into any system to make sure that it's
actually correct yeah that would be a
great idea for a show so maybe we'll do
a future show on that sounds good yeah
Donny thank you very much for speaking
to software engineering radio
thank you very much for having me on the
podcast for software engineering radio
this has been Robert bloomin you can
reach us by email team @ SC - video
dotnet find our group on facebook or
linkedin and on twitter at SC radio
thank you for listening thanks for
listening to SC radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website @ SC -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on itunes
mention a message us on twitter at SC
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team @ SC - radio net this and all
other episodes of SU radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]